<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the objections of the citizens of York, against the bill for making navigable the rivers Aire and Calder</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3428AB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896562</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">134548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 134548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2416:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the objections of the citizens of York, against the bill for making navigable the rivers Aire and Calder</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>River engineering --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inland navigation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Aire River (England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Calder, River (West Yorkshire, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:134548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE OBJECTIONS OF THE Citizens of YORK, AGAINST The Bill for making Navigable the Rivers <hi>Aire</hi> and <hi>Calder.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is objected, <q>That if theſe Rivers (or either of them) be made Navigable, it will ſo drain and leſſen the Tide of <hi>Ouze,</hi> as to render that River <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnavigable for the future, to the great Dammage of the City of <hi>York.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer thereto, It is humbly conceived, that it can have no ſuch Effect for the following Reaſons:
<list>
                  <item>1st, The Objection does not reach the River <hi>Calder,</hi> for that River empties it ſelf into <hi>Aire,</hi> many Miles above the Flowing of the Tide; ſo that whatſoever is done upon that River cannot affects the Tides, and therefore is out of the Queſtion.</item>
                  <item>2ly, Nor has the Objection any greater force againſt making the River <hi>Aire</hi> Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable; For tho' the Cauſe of the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea is not yet diſcovered, yet it muſt be granted, That the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea is the only Cauſe of the Tide in all Rivers where it is; And that the Effect neceſſarily attends this Cauſe is Matter of Fact and Daily Obſervation, the Tides being always greater or leſs, as the Waters riſe more or leſs at Sea; And the greateſt Rivers are filled as high <hi>(viz.)</hi> as near to a Level with the Swelling of the Sea, as the leaſt are, every Tide, tho' they contain a hundred times as much Water; and conſequently, tho' the whole County of <hi>York</hi> were dug into a Pond, or Receptacle for Water, it could not leſſen the Tide in any other proportion than the Water contained in that Receptacle would bear to the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Seas, from whence it was ſupplied; and that quantity of Water would be but a ſmall part of the whole, and could not abate the Surface of the Tide-Water a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an Inch: For Water acts mechanically and neceſſarily, as a heavy fluid Body, and will flow naturally to all Places where the Surface is lower than the Place it flows from, and fill them all (tho' never ſo large) till all the Surface is at equal diſtance from the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and then it becomes its own poiſe and is at reſt: From whence it plainly follows, That nothing can be done upon the River <hi>Aire,</hi> to leſſen ſenſibly the Tide of <hi>Ouze.</hi>
                     <p>There might be given many Inſtances to confirm this Argument, (were it needful) As when the Banks break in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> (which often happens) whereby the Receptacle for the Tide-Water is much more inlarged than can be pretended in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe, and yet the Tide in the next Rivers not leſſened (to ſenſe). Likewiſe, ſince the breaking of the Banks upon the River <hi>Thames</hi> (in <hi>Eſſex</hi>) whereby the Outlet for the Water has been greater than is feared in this Caſe, the Tides have not been leſs at <hi>London</hi>-bridge.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>3ly, But admitting there were any force in this Objection, it makes for the Navigation of <hi>Aire,</hi> and not againſt it; For, if the making the Receptacle for Water in the River <hi>Aire</hi> greater, will leſſen the Tide in the River <hi>Ouze</hi> (as objected)—Then the making the Receptacle in the River <hi>Aire</hi> leſs, will increaſe the Tide in the River <hi>Ouze.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And that is what the Undertakers for <hi>Aire</hi> will do, (if they alter the River at all) for they will make the Courſe or Channel of the River ſtraiter, and then the Water taking this new Courſe, the old crooked Channel will ſoon fill up, and conſequently the River <hi>Aire</hi> contain leſs Water than before, being made much ſhorter and narrower than it was. But if they do not alter or meddle with the River <hi>Aire</hi> within the flowing of the Tide, (as is moſt likely) Then this Objection reacheth the Navigation of <hi>Aire</hi> no more than <hi>Calder,</hi> but anſwers it ſelf.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
